<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Mijian Xu</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/</link><atom:link href="https://home.xumijian.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Mijian Xu</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2021} Mijian Xu</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:27:16 +0800</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://home.xumijian.me/media/icon_hub2b2f91bac16cc9a5275f87cc6d0a961_12088_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Mijian Xu</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/</link></image><item><title>Full-waveform inversion joint with multiple data types</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/jointat/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:27:16 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/jointat/</guid><description>&lt;p>Different data types have different sensitivities to different anomalies. For example, ambient noise surface wave data has good lateral resolution in shallow depth, while teleseismic waveform and receiver function data have good vertical resolution. By combining multiple data types within the framework of full-waveform inversion (adjoint tomography) and jointly optimizing the velocity model, we can obtain a more reliable and accurate velocity structure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Receiver Function Adjoint Tomography</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/rfat/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 10:24:27 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/rfat/</guid><description>&lt;p>A new technique for P-wave receiver function (PRF) inversion, within the framework of wave equation-based adjoint tomography and referred to as RFAT, has been developed to obtain models of Vp, Vs, and density. This innovative technique fits the synthetic PRFs with observed PRFs and can better image the lateral variations of Vs from the crust to the uppermost mantle than traditional 1-D PRF inversion. We utilized RFAT to perform high-resolution imaging beneath a dense seismic array in Southeastern Tibet, revealing low-velocity zones (LVZs) extending from the uppermost mantle to the crust, as well as an eastward dipping Moho under the Red River Fault (RRF). Our inversion results provide direct evidence for the existence of a distinct asthenospheric upwelling channel beneath the RRF, and further highlight the effectiveness of RFAT for accurately imaging subsurface structures.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seispy: Python Module for Batch Calculation and Postprocessing of Receiver Functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/seispy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 22:33:40 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/seispy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seispy is a graphical interface Python module for receiver function (RF) calculation and post-processing in seismological research. Automated workflows of RF calculations facilitate processing large volumes of different types of seismic data. The graphical user interface enables an intuitive and straightforward evaluation of RF quality. All parameters about the pre-processing for RF estimation can be adjusted based on user preference. Water-level frequency-domain deconvolution and iterative time-domain deconvolution for RF estimation are available in Seispy. The current version of Seispy contains five main modules for the post-processing of RF such as H-k stacking, crustal anisotropic estimation, harmonic decomposition, 2D and 3D Common Conversion Point (CCP) stacking. The CCP stacking in the different application scenarios can be handled by a rich collection of modules, such as time-to-depth conversion, 2D or 3D CCP stacking, and adaptive station or bin selection for CCP stacking profiles in a dense seismic array or a linear seismic array. As a Python module, functions in the Seispy can be called easily in python scripts for other purposes. The modular design allows new functionality to be added in a collaborative development environment. Licensed under GPLv3, Seispy allow users and developers to freely use, change, share and distribute copies of the package.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Crustal Structures in the SE Tibet</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-crust/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 22:24:27 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-crust/</guid><description>&lt;p>The tectonic uplift of the Tibetan Plateau is a focus in the geosciences. Mid‐lower crustal flow is a popular model to interpret the geodynamic mechanism on the margin of the Tibetan Plateau. The model predicts different surface and Moho topographies across the plateau boundary due to the different strengths of the surrounding blocks, i.e., sharp boundaries on the eastern plateau boundary and gentle variations in the southeastern plateau boundary. Here, we employ receiver function and common conversion point stacking analysis with the seismic waveforms recorded by the dense ChinArray and other local seismic stations to accurately define the Moho topography in SE Tibet. We find that the Moho under the Tibetan Plateau is much deeper than that under the surrounding Yangtze Craton and Indochina block; abrupt Moho changes are found across the southeastern plateau margin, similar to that under the eastern plateau margin. We interpret these sharp Moho variations across the plateau margin to have developed when the Tibetan Plateau was extruded southeastward in the late Miocene. Subsequent gravity collapse resulted in crustal extension and gentle topographic variation, while the sharp Moho slope was preserved.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mantle Transition Zone Structure in SE Tibet</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 21:49:32 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/</guid><description>&lt;p>The subduction of the Indian Plate beneath SE Tibet and its related volcanism in Tengchong are important geologic processes that accompany the evolution of the Tibetan Plateau. However, it is still not clear whether the subduction and volcanism are confined to the upper mantle or if they extend deep into the mantle transition zone (MTZ). Here, we imaged MTZ structures by using receiver function methods with the waveforms recorded by more than 300 temporary stations in SE Tibet. The results show significant depressions of both the 410-km and 660-km discontinuities and a thickened MTZ (260–280 km) beneath SE Tibet. The depression of the 660-km discontinuity (by 10–30 km) and the thickened MTZ correlate well with high P-wave velocity anomalies in the MTZ, indicating the presence of a subducted Indian slab within the MTZ. Significant depression of the 410-km discontinuity (by 10–20 km) beneath the Tengchong volcano indicates that the volcano originates from the MTZ and is closely related to the subducted Indian slab. Our results confirm the deep subduction of the Indian plate and the deep origin of the Tengchong volcano. However, it remains unknown whether a slab gap exists and contributes to the Tengchong volcano.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-comparison-of-the-stacked-p-wave-receiver-functions-and-the-p-wave-velocity-anomalies-huang-et-al-2015aalong-the-three-profiles-shown-in-the-bottom-right-figure-blue-and-red-colors-in-background-denote-high-and-low-velocities-respectively-black-and-gray-lines-denote-the-average-p-wave-receiver-functions-and-their-95-confidence-level-respectively-obtained-from-2000-bootstrapping-iterations-see-the-text-for-details-red-and-blue-colors-denote-the-significant-positive-and-negative-pulses-respectively-two-dashed-horizontal-lines-denote-the-410-km-and-660-km-depths-for-reference-the-red-triangle-denotes-the-tengchong-volcano">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SE Tibet NTZ" srcset="
/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_024d72963bac0a46382fd3c92fb8da3e.png 400w,
/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_8c85b75df2399bff4791121f8ec3c93d.png 760w,
/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w"
src="https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_024d72963bac0a46382fd3c92fb8da3e.png"
width="760"
height="467"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption data-pre="Figure&amp;nbsp;" data-post=":&amp;nbsp;" class="numbered">
Comparison of the stacked P-wave receiver functions and the P-wave velocity anomalies (Huang et al., 2015a)along the three profiles shown in the bottom-right figure. Blue and red colors in background denote high and low velocities, respectively. Black and gray lines denote the average P-wave receiver functions and their 95% confidence level, respectively, obtained from 2,000 bootstrapping iterations (see the text for details). Red and blue colors denote the significant positive and negative pulses, respectively. Two dashed horizontal lines denote the 410 km and 660 km depths for reference. The red triangle denotes the Tengchong volcano.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Seispy: Python Module for Batch Calculation and Postprocessing of Receiver Functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/srl2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/srl2022/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Hydrous melting driven upwelling from the mantle transition zone in the Mongolia Plateau revealed by receiver function analysis</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022-he/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022-he/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>A relic thickened crustal root beneath the Cenozoic rift zone of the NW Ordos margin, North China, revealed by receiver functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2022/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 14:24:33 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Crustal and Uppermost Mantle Heterogeneities Across the Ailaoshan Red River Shear Zone, SE Tibet: Implications for Cenozoic Magmatic Activity</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022b/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Moho Complexity in Southern California Revealed by Local PmP and Teleseismic Ps Waves</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022a/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2022a/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Seispy: Python module for batch calculation and post-processing of receiver functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/talk/seispy-python-module-for-batch-calculation-and-post-processing-of-receiver-functions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/talk/seispy-python-module-for-batch-calculation-and-post-processing-of-receiver-functions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Layered crustal anisotropy and deformation in the SE Tibetan plateau revealed by Markov-Chain-Monte-Carlo inversion of receiver functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020b/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 14:24:33 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sharp lateral Moho variations across the SE Tibetan margin and their implications for plateau growth</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 11:14:55 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tectonic evolution of the eastern margin of the Tibetan plateau: Insight from crustal structures using P wave receiver functions</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jaes2020/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 23:08:33 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jaes2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lateral variation of the mantle transition zone beneath the Tibetan Plateau: Insight into thermal processes during Indian–Asian collision</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020a/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 14:24:33 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Insight into the subducted Indian slab and origin of the Tengchong volcano in SE Tibet from receiver function analysis</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2018/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2018/</guid><description/></item><item><title>SplitRFLab: A MATLAB GUI toolbox for receiver function analysis based on SplitLab</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/es2016/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 23:15:13 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/es2016/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mantle structure and dynamics beneath SE Tibet revealed by new seismic images</title><link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2015/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2015/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title/><link>https://home.xumijian.me/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://home.xumijian.me/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>