<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mijian Xu</title>
    <link>https://home.xumijian.me/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://home.xumijian.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mijian Xu</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 14:24:33 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Mijian Xu</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crustal Structures in the SE Tibet</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-crust/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 22:24:27 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-crust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The tectonic uplift of the Tibetan Plateau is a focus in the geosciences. Mid‐lower crustal flow is a popular model to interpret the geodynamic mechanism on the margin of the Tibetan Plateau. The model predicts different surface and Moho topographies across the plateau boundary due to the different strengths of the surrounding blocks, i.e., sharp boundaries on the eastern plateau boundary and gentle variations in the southeastern plateau boundary. Here, we employ receiver function and common conversion point stacking analysis with the seismic waveforms recorded by the dense ChinArray and other local seismic stations to accurately define the Moho topography in SE Tibet. We find that the Moho under the Tibetan Plateau is much deeper than that under the surrounding Yangtze Craton and Indochina block; abrupt Moho changes are found across the southeastern plateau margin, similar to that under the eastern plateau margin. We interpret these sharp Moho variations across the plateau margin to have developed when the Tibetan Plateau was extruded southeastward in the late Miocene. Subsequent gravity collapse resulted in crustal extension and gentle topographic variation, while the sharp Moho slope was preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mantle Transition Zone Structure in SE Tibet</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 21:49:32 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subduction of the Indian Plate beneath SE Tibet and its related volcanism in Tengchong are important geologic processes that accompany the evolution of the Tibetan Plateau. However, it is still not clear whether the subduction and volcanism are confined to the upper mantle or if they extend deep into the mantle transition zone (MTZ). Here, we imaged MTZ structures by using receiver function methods with the waveforms recorded by more than 300 temporary stations in SE Tibet. The results show significant depressions of both the 410-km and 660-km discontinuities and a thickened MTZ (260–280 km) beneath SE Tibet. The depression of the 660-km discontinuity (by 10–30 km) and the thickened MTZ correlate well with high P-wave velocity anomalies in the MTZ, indicating the presence of a subducted Indian slab within the MTZ. Significant depression of the 410-km discontinuity (by 10–20 km) beneath the Tengchong volcano indicates that the volcano originates from the MTZ and is closely related to the subducted Indian slab. Our results confirm the deep subduction of the Indian plate and the deep origin of the Tengchong volcano. However, it remains unknown whether a slab gap exists and contributes to the Tengchong volcano.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-topography-of-mtz-under-se-tibet&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Topography of MTZ under SE Tibet.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://home.xumijian.me/project/se-tibet-mtz/mtz_huda8dedbf548e4fb74e14a01b0894f55e_1931777_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;SE Tibet NTZ&#34; width=&#34;1421&#34; height=&#34;874&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Topography of MTZ under SE Tibet.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Layered crustal anisotropy and deformation in the SE Tibetan plateau revealed by Markov-Chain-Monte-Carlo inversion of receiver functions</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 14:24:33 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharp lateral Moho variations across the SE Tibetan margin and their implications for plateau growth</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 11:14:55 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jgr2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tectonic evolution of the eastern margin of the Tibetan plateau: Insight from crustal structures using P wave receiver functions</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jaes2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 23:08:33 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/jaes2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lateral variation of the mantle transition zone beneath the Tibetan Plateau: Insight into thermal processes during Indian–Asian collision</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020a/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 14:24:33 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/pepi2020a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SplitRFLab</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/project/splitrflab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 22:33:40 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/project/splitrflab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We add new modules for receiver function (RF) analysis in SplitLab toolbox, which includes the manual RF analysis module, automatic RF analysis and related quality control modules, and H-k stacking module. The updated toolbox (named SplitRFLab toolbox), espe- cially its automatic RF analysis module, could calculate the RFs quickly and efficiently, which is very useful in RF analysis with huge amount of seismic data. China is now conducting the ChinArray project that plans to deploy thousands of portable stations across Chinese mainland. Our SplitRFLab toolbox may obtain reliable RF results quickly at the first time, which provide essentially new constraint to the crustal and mantle structures.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://home.xumijian.me/project/splitrflab/workflow_huac64a2eabaea5c42cb92d29bd5e54d91_240330_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://home.xumijian.me/project/splitrflab/workflow_huac64a2eabaea5c42cb92d29bd5e54d91_240330_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1240&#34; height=&#34;1753&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insight into the subducted Indian slab and origin of the Tengchong volcano in SE Tibet from receiver function analysis</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SplitRFLab: A MATLAB GUI toolbox for receiver function analysis based on SplitLab</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/es2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 23:15:13 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/es2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mantle structure and dynamics beneath SE Tibet revealed by new seismic images</title>
      <link>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 23:08:33 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://home.xumijian.me/publication/epsl2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
